<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3311 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4028 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4028.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-sessiontimer-race-latest" obsoletes="" updates="4028" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Session timer glare">
      Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Session Timer Glare Handling
    </title>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
  
    <date year="2017"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SIP</keyword>
    <keyword>session timer</keyword>
    <keyword>Session-Expires</keyword>
    <keyword>491</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document updates RFC 4028, by clarifying the procedures for negotiating usage of the 
        Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) session timer mechansim, in order to avoid a race condition 
        where both endpoints trigger simultaneous negotiations.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC4028"></xref> defines a mechanism, where periodic SIP requests are sent
        in order to allow SIP user agents and proxies to determine whether a SIP session is
        still active. 
      </t>
      <t>
        The usage of the mechanism is negotiated using two new SIP header fields (Session-Expires
        and Min-SE), a new option tag ('timer') and a new SIP response code (422). 
      </t>
      <section title="Problem Statement" toc="default">
        <t>
          1. Section 7.4 of <xref target="RFC4028"></xref> says that, in a session refresh request sent
          within a dialog with an active session timer, the Session-Expires header field should
          be included in the request. However, the text is unclear regarding including the
          Session-Expires header field in a session refresh request when a negotiation of session
          timer usage is still ongoing, e.g., if one user agent is sending a request that contains
          a Session-Expires header field and, before it receives the associated 2xx response, receives
          a request from the peer user agent that also contains a Session-Expires header field. Such
          scenario might cause a glare situation, with conflicting negotiation parameters.
        </t>
        <t>
          2. The absence of the Session-Expires header field in a 2xx response to an (re-)INVITE 
          request <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> or UPDATE request <xref target="RFC3311"></xref> 
          means that the mechanism isn't used. This can be used to reject the usage of the mechanism 
          when sending a response. However, the text is unclear that this only applies to cases where 
          the associated SIP request contained a Session-Expires header field.  
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Solution" toc="default">
        <t>
          This document updates <xref target="RFC4028"></xref>, by clarifying the procedures for 
          negotiating usage of the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> 
          session timer mechanism <xref target="RFC4028"></xref>. The following clarifications are 
          provided:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              A Session-Expires header field can only be included in a session refresh request if
              there is no ongoing negotiation of usage of the session timer mechansim.
            </t>
            <t>
              A user agent shall, if it receives a session request with a Session-Expires header field
              during an ongoing negotiation of usage of the session timer mechanism, send a 491
              (Request Pending) response to the request.
            </t>
            <t>
              The absence of a Session-Expires header field in a response will disable usage of
              the session timer mechanism only if the associated requuest contained a Session-Expires
              header field.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
 
    <section title="Conventions">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section.rfcupdate.4028" title="Update to RFC 4028">
      <section anchor="section.rfcupdate.4028.7-2" title="Update to Section 7.2">
        <t>
            This section updates the third paragraph in section 7.2 of
            <xref target="RFC4028" pageno="false" format="default"/>, by 
            clarifying that the absence of a Session-Expires header field in
            a response will disable usage of the session timer mechanism only
            if the associated request contained a Session-Expires header field.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

OLD TEXT:

   If the 2xx response did not contain a Session-Expires header field,
   there is no session expiration. In this case, no refreshes need to
   be sent. A 2xx without a Session-Expires can come for both initial
   and subsequent session refresh requests. This means that the session
   timer can be 'turned-off' in mid dialog by receiving a response
   without a Session-Expires header field.


NEW TEXT:

   If the request contained a Session-Expires header field, and the
   associated 2xx response did not contain a Session-Expires header
   field, there is no session expiration. In this case, no refreshes
   need to be sent. A 2xx without a Session-Expires can come for both
   initial and subsequent session refresh requests. This means that
   the session timer can be 'turned-off' in mid dialog by receiving a
   response without a Session-Expires header field.

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="section.rfcupdate.4028.7-4" title="Update to Section 7.4">
        <t>
            This section updates the fifth paragraph in section 7.4 of
            <xref target="RFC4028" pageno="false" format="default"/>, by 
            clarifying that the Session-Expires header field can only be
            included in a refresh request if there is no ongoing negotiation
            of usage of the session timer mechanism.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

OLD TEXT:

   In a session refresh request sent within a dialog with an active
   session timer, the Session-Expires header field SHOULD be present.
   When present, it SHOULD be equal to the maximum of the Min-SE header
   field (recall that its default value when not present is 90 seconds)
   and the current session interval. Inclusion of the Session-Expires
   header field with this value avoids certain denial-of-service
   attacks, as documented in Section 11. As such, a UA should only
   ignore the SHOULD in unusual and singular cases where it is 
   desirable to change the session interval mid-dialog.


NEW TEXT:

   In a session refresh request sent within a dialog with an active
   session timer, and when there is no ongoing negotiation of usage
   of the session timer mechanism, the Session-Expires header field 
   SHOULD be present. If there is an ongoing negotiation, the
   Session-Expires header field MUST NOT be present. When present, it
   SHOULD be equal to the maximum of the Min-SE header field (recall
   that its default value when not present is 90 seconds) and the 
   current session interval. Inclusion of the Session-Expires header
   field with this value avoids certain denial-of-service attacks, as
   documented in Section 11. As such, a UA should only ignore the 
   SHOULD in unusual and singular cases where it is desirable to 
   change the session interval mid-dialog.

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="section.rfcupdate.4028.8-1" title="Update to Section 8.1">
        <t>
            This section updates the second paragraph section 8.1 of <xref target="RFC4028" 
            pageno="false" format="default"/>, by clarifying that a proxy can
            insert a Session-Expires header field in a request only if there is 
            no ongoing negotiation of usage of the session timer mechanism.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

OLD TEXT:

   To request a session timer for a session, a proxy makes sure that a
   Session-Expires header field is present in a session refresh request
   for that session. A proxy MAY insert a Session-Expires header field
   in the request before forwarding it if none was present in the
   request. This Session-Expires header field may contain any desired
   expiration time the proxy would like, but not with a duration lower
   than the value in the Min-SE header field in the request, if it is
   present. The proxy MUST NOT include a refresher parameter in the
   header field value.

NEW TEXT:

   To request a session timer for a session, a proxy makes sure that a
   Session-Expires header field is present in a session refresh request
   for that session. A proxy MAY insert a Session-Expires header field
   in the request before forwarding it if none was present in the
   request, and if there is no ongoing negotiation of usage of the
   session timer mechanism. This Session-Expires header field may 
   contain any desired expiration time the proxy would like, but not 
   with a duration lower than the value in the Min-SE header field in 
   the request, if it is present. The proxy MUST NOT include a refresher 
   parameter in the header field value.

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="section.rfcupdate.4028.9" title="Update to Section 9">
        <t>
            This section updates section 8.1 of <xref target="RFC4028" 
            pageno="false" format="default"/>, by clarifying that a session 
            refresh request that is received while there is an ongoing 
            negotiation of usage of the session timer mechanism shall be 
            rejected by a 491 (Request Pending) response. The clarification 
            is done by adding a new paragraph between the fouth and fifth
            paragraphs of the section.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

NEW TEXT:

   If an incoming request contains a Session-Expires header field,
   and there is on ongoing negotiation of usage of the session timer
   mechanism, the UAS MUST reject the request with a 491 (Request 
   Pending) response.

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section.sec" title="Security considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations associated with the SIP Session-Timer
        mechanism are described in <xref target="RFC4028" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        This specification adds clarification text for avoiding session-timer negotiation
        race conditions, and does not introduce new security considerations.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA considerations">
      <t>
        This specification makes no requests from IANA.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3311"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4028"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
